<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!--
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
]>
-->
<!-- <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?> -->
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs), 
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-rdb-ohai-feedback-to-proxy-04"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Oblivious Relay Feedback">Oblivious Relay Feedback</title>

    <author fullname="Tirumaleswar Reddy" initials="T." surname="Reddy">
      <organization>Nokia</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>kondtir@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dan Wing" initials="D." surname="Wing">
      <organization abbrev="Citrix">Citrix Systems, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>4988 Great America Pkwy</street>

          <city>Santa Clara</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95054</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>danwing@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Mohamed Boucadair" initials="M." surname="Boucadair">
      <organization>Orange</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city>Rennes</city>

          <region></region>

          <code>35000</code>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>mohamed.boucadair@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Roberto Polli" initials="R." surname="Polli">
      <organization>Team Digitale, Italian Government</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>

          <city></city>

          <region></region>

          <code></code>

          <country></country>
        </postal>

        <email>robipolli@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date />

    <workgroup>ohai</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>To provide equitable service to clients, servers often rate-limit
      incoming requests, for example, based upon the source IP address.
      However, oblivious HTTP removes the ability for the server to
      distinguish amongst clients so the server can only rate-limit traffic
      from the oblivious relay. This harms all clients behind that oblivious
      relay.</t>

      <t>This specification enables a server to convey rate-limit information
      to an oblivious relay, which can use it to apply rate-limit policies on
      clients. Cooperating oblivious relays can thus provide more equitable
      service to their distinguishable clients without impacting on all
      clients behind that oblivious relay.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>Oblivious HTTP <xref target="OHTTP"></xref> requires three parties to
      exchange HTTP messages: the client, the relay, and the target (formally,
      the Oblivious Gateway Resource and Oblivious Target Resource). Oblivious
      HTTP enables a client to send requests to a target in such a way that
      the target cannot tell whether two requests came from the same client,
      and the relay cannot see the contents of the requests.</t>

      <t>Since clients are located behind a relay, a target cannot distinguish
      between well-behaving and malicious clients: an unexpected behavior from
      one or more clients can then impact on all the intermediated clients, as
      described in Section 8.2.1 of <xref target="OHTTP"></xref>. This can be
      problematic when the target implements rate limiting policies based on
      an information masked by the intermediary, such as the source IP
      address.</t>

      <t>This document defines a mechanism that allows Oblivious gateway and
      target resource to provide rate-limit information to an Oblivious relay
      via the RateLimit fields defined in <xref target="RATELIMIT"></xref>.
      This is useful when such servers identify traffic anomalies or
      unexpected request volumes. The Oblivious relay can then use this
      information to apply rate-limit policies on clients.</t>

      <t>While <xref target="RATELIMIT"></xref> provides enough information to
      generic clients to shape their request policy and avoid being throttled
      out, this specification allows an Oblivious gateway and target resource
      to indicate their RateLimit information is intended for the Oblivious
      relay (rather than to the client).</t>

      <t>How an Oblivious relay can use this information to avoid being
      throttled out or shape its request policy is outside the scope of this
      specification.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="notation" title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
      <xref target="RFC2119"></xref><xref target="RFC8174"></xref> when, and
      only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>

      <t>The terms "content", "receiver", "request", and "response" are to be
      interpreted as described in <xref format="default"
      target="HTTP"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The terms "Encapsulated request", "Encapsulated response", "Oblivious
      relay resource", "Oblivious gateway resource", "Oblivious target
      resource", and "Client" are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="OHTTP"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The collective term "Oblivious resource" indicates either an
      "Oblivious gateway resource" or an "Oblivious target resource".</t>

      <t>The terms "quota policy", "service limit", "expiring limit", and
      "RateLimit fields" are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RATELIMIT"></xref>.</t>

      <t>This document uses the Integer type from <xref
      target="STRUCTURED-FIELDS"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="provision"
             title="Providing RateLimit Information to an Oblivious Proxy ">
      <t>An Oblivious resource that uses RateLimit fields <xref
      target="RATELIMIT"></xref> to return service limit information MAY add
      the "ohttp-target" quota policy parameter defined in <xref
      target="feedback"></xref> to signal to the receiver that the associated
      quota policy is intended for an Oblivious relay. For example, when an
      Oblivious target identifies a high frequency or high volume anomalies in
      the HTTP requests it would include the "ohttp-target" parameter.</t>

      <t>The term "Oblivious Relay Feedback" denotes both the mechanism
      described in this specification and the complete set of RateLimit fields
      together with the "ohttp-target" parameter.</t>

      <t>To know whether the RateLimit fields provides Oblivious Relay
      Feedback (see Section 3.1), an Oblivious relay MUST: <list
          style="numbers">
          <t>Identify the quota policy associated to the expiring limit.</t>

          <t>Check whether the "ohttp-target" parameter is present and its
          syntax is correct.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t>In the example shown in <xref target="poex1"></xref>, the expiring
      limit value is "100", so the associated quota policy is the second one.
      This quota policy includes the "ohttp-target" parameter: this indicates
      that the RateLimit fields are intended for an Oblivious relay.</t>

      <t><figure anchor="poex1"
          title="An Example of Oblivious Proxy Feedback.">
          <artwork><![CDATA[   
   RateLimit-Limit: 100
   RateLimit-Policy: 10;w=1, 100;w=60;ohttp-target=1
   RateLimit-Remaining: 8
   RateLimit-Reset: 15]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="feedback" title="The ohttp-target Quota Policy Parameter">
      <section title="ohttp-target Parameter">
        <t>The following quota policy parameter is defined for the
        RateLimit-Policy field <xref target="RATELIMIT"></xref>:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="ohttp-target:">Indicates that the associated quota
            policy provides Oblivious Relay Feedback. This parameter is
            OPTIONAL.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>The "ohttp-target" parameter has the following syntax:</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[ohttp-target = sf-integer
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>Its value MUST be an Integer (Section 3.3.1 of <xref
        target="STRUCTURED-FIELDS"></xref>) and indicates whether the quota
        policy is applicable to all the clients that are serviced by the
        Oblivious relay or applicable only to a specific client. The
        "ohttp-target" parameter MUST have one of the following values:</t>

        <t><list style="hanging">
            <t hangText="1:">Indicates that RateLimit fields are applicable to
            all the clients that are serviced by the same Oblivious relay.</t>

            <t hangText="2:">Indicates that RateLimit fields are applicable
            only to the offending client. For example, this value is used if
            the client is attacking the server (e.g., the client is using an
            abnormal header that matches an attack pattern). The mechanisms
            Oblivious relay can use to rate-limit the traffic from the client
            but at the same time prevent the target to correlate requests from
            clients are discussed in <xref target="mechanism"></xref>.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>Other values MUST cause the parameter to be ignored.</t>

        <t>The "ohttp-target" parameter MUST NOT appear more than once in a
        quota policy. If the parameter is malformed or its value is invalid,
        it MUST be ignored, and the receiving Oblivious relay MUST NOT attempt
        to fix neither the parameter nor its value. That is, the RateLimit
        fields must not be considered as providing Oblivious Relay
        Feedback.</t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="proc" title="Processing the ohttp-target Parameter">
        <t>An Oblivious relay receiving RateLimit fields providing Oblivious
        Relay Feedback will do the following:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>It MUST remove the RateLimit fields from the response, since
            they are not intended to be forwarded to clients.</t>

            <t>It MAY add a new set of RateLimit fields that are intended to
            be forwarded to a client.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>An Oblivious gateway resource receiving RateLimit fields providing
        Oblivious Relay Feedback MUST proceed as follows:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>Remove the RateLimit fields from the HTTP response, since they
            are not intended to be forwarded to the client. It, then,
            encapsulates the HTTP response.</t>

            <t>Add the above RateLimit fields to the response containing the
            encapsulated response sent to the Oblivious relay, so that the
            Oblivious relay can access them.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>If the RateLimit fields along with the "ohttp-target" parameter are
        generated by the Oblivious gateway resource before removing the
        protection (including being unable to remove the encapsulation for any
        reason)(Section 6.2 of <xref target="OHTTP"></xref>), it will result
        in the RateLimit fields added in the response being sent without
        protection in response to a POST request from a client.</t>

        <t>While this specification does not mandate specific traffic shaping
        actions for Oblivious proxies in addition to the ones indicated in
        <xref target="RATELIMIT"></xref>, an Oblivious relay failing to
        reshape traffic from a specific client or from all the clients
        according to the received Oblivious Relay Feedback can experience
        different levels of service denial by the Oblivious gateway and target
        resources. There is no explicit mechanism for an Oblivious relay to
        indicate to the server that the rate-limit information was processed
        or was ignored.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="mechanism" title="Prevent Client identification">
      <t>The following mechanisms can be used by an Oblivious relay to
      process "ohttp-target" parameter with value set to 2 :</t>

      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t>The Oblivious relay does not immediately act to rate-limit the
          traffic from the client but starts maintaining a count of responses
          to the client with "ohttp-target" parameter value set to "2" marked
          as "potential malicious requests" and responses without the
          parameter marked as "legitimate requests". The Oblivious relay can
          rate-limit requests from the offending client for a certain duration
          only when the client has a high ratio of "potential malicious
          requests" to "legitimate requests". In other words, the Oblivious
          relay will rate-limit requests from a client if the target has seen
          an attack pattern in multiple requests from that same client. A
          malicious client sends malformed HTTP requests, whereas a benign
          client sends valid HTTP requests. The malformed HTTP requests are
          linkable whereas the valid HTTP requests are not linkable. Most
          importantly, the target will not be able to partition the anonymity
          set of legitimate clients.</t>

          <t>The Oblivious relay enforces the delayed rate-limiting of the
          offending client discussed in step 1 provided a large number of
          clients are actively using the relay and the total number of benign
          clients is significantly a large number compared to offending
          clients (e.g., total clients is greater than hundred thousand and
          benign clients is above eighty percent of the total clients). This
          way the anonymity set of benign clients will be a relatively larger
          number even after rate-limiting the offending clients.</t>

          <t>The Oblivious relay acts to rate-limit the client provided it has
          a bad reputation score (Many security network security vendors offer
          client reputation score, for instance, see <xref
          target="Reputation"></xref>).</t>

          <t>The Oblivious relay provider hosts a honeypot of clients to send
          good traffic to the server. The relay checks if it receives the
          ohttp-target parameter set to 2 for these benign clients to identify
          if the target is misbehaving. For example, if the target is is
          oblivious DoH server, these clients can send a mix of queries to the
          top one million domains and sensitive domains (e.g., Health,
          Ethnicity, Religion, Sexual Orientation, Political Beliefs, Adult
          etc). If the Oblivious relay receives "ohttp-target" parameter with
          value set to 2 for these clients, it would identify the target is
          misbehaving and ignores the targeted rate-limit for any other client
          it is serving.</t>

          <t>The Oblivious relay can introduce synthetic encapsulated requests
          to simulate equal distribution of sequence of requests to avoid any
          request correlation by the target.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="header"
             title="The attack-severity Quota Policy Parameter">
      <t>The following quota policy parameter is defined for the
      RateLimit-Policy field defined in <xref target="RATELIMIT"></xref>:</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="attack-severity:">Is used by the Oblivious resource to
          convey the likeliness that an HTTP request is malicious. This
          parameter is OPTIONAL.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[attack-severity = sf-string
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>Note that sf-string is defined in Section 3.3.3 of <xref
      target="STRUCTURED-FIELDS"></xref>.</t>

      <t>The value of the "attack-severity" parameter is a String (Section
      3.3.3 of <xref target="RFC8941"></xref>) that takes one of the values
      defined in <xref target="SEVERITY"></xref>. This parameter MUST NOT
      appear more than once in a quota policy. If the parameter is malformed
      or its value is invalid, the parameter MUST be ignored, and the relays
      MUST NOT attempt to fix neither the parameter nor the value.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="example"
             title="Use of The ohttp-target Quota Policy Parameters: An Example">
      <t>The example depicted in <xref target="poex"></xref> illustrates the
      use of the "ohttp-target" parameter. An oblivious target resource
      receives a malformed request and uses the source IP address to identify
      that it was an encapsulated request decapsulated by an oblivious gateway
      resource. The Oblivious target resource generates a 400 response and
      adds the RateLimit fields along with the "ohttp-target" quota policy
      parameter. The oblivious gateway resource proceeds as follows: <list
          style="numbers">
          <t>Copy the RateLimit fields from the original response.</t>

          <t>Remove them from the original response before encapsulating
          it.</t>

          <t>Generate a single 200 response containing the encapsulated
          response for the oblivious relay resource along with the copied
          RateLimit fields.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t><figure anchor="poex"
          title="An Example of Ratelimit Feedback to Proxy">
          <artwork><![CDATA[+----+            +----------+       +----------+    +----------+
| C  |            | Relay    |       | Gateway  |    | Target   |
|    |            | Resource |       | Resource |    | Resource |
+-+--+            +----+-----+       +-----+----+    +-----+----+
  |                    |                   |               |                    
  | Encapsulated       |                   |               |
  +------------------->|                   |               |
  |  Request           |                   |               |
  |                    | Encapsulated      |               |
  |                    +------------------>|               |
  |                    |  Request          |               |
  |                    |                   | Request       | .---------.
  |                    |                   +-------------->| | Identify|
  |                    |                   |               +-+malformed|
  |                    |                   |               | | request |
  |                    |                   |  400 response | '---------'
  |                    |                   |<--------------+
  |                    |                   |               |
  |                    | 200 response with |               |
  |                    | RateLimit-Limit,  |               |
  |                    | RateLimit-Policy  |               |
  |                    | fields and the    |               | 
  |                    | ohttp-target      |               |
  |                    | parameter         |               |
                       |<------------------+               |
.--------------------. | Encapsulated 400  |               |
| Process            | |    response       |               |    
| ohttp-target       +-+                   |               |
| and rate-limit     |  |                  |               |                       
| requests from the  |  |                  |               |                     
| offending client   |  |                  |               |                     
'--------------------'  |                  |               |
                        |                  |               |
  |                     |                  |               |
  | Encapsulated 400    |                  |               |
  |<--------------------+                  |               |
  |     response        |                  |               |
  |                     |                  |               |
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>

      <t>The response that is generated by the Oblivious gateway resource is
      depicted in <xref target="res"></xref>. This response includes an
      unregistered, informative "comment" quota policy parameter providing the
      rationale for the "attack- severity".</t>

      <t><figure anchor="res" title="Example of a Response">
          <artwork><![CDATA[=============== NOTE: '\' line wrapping per RFC 8792 ================

  HTTP/1.1 200 OK  
  Date: Wed, 27 March 2022 04:45:07 GMT 
  Cache-Control: private, no-store 
  RateLimit-Limit: 10
  RateLimit-Policy: 10;ohttp-target=2;attack-severity="high";\
comment="abnormal header matching a WAF rule"
  Content-Type: message/ohttp-res
  Content-Length: 38 <content is the encapsulated 400 response>
  ...encrypted content...
]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Ohai-Outside-Encap" title="Ohttp-Outside-Encap Header">
      <t>The "Ohttp-Outside-Encap" header is defined in this specification
      (<xref target="new-header"></xref>). Its purpose is to signal which HTTP
      headers will be removed by the Oblivious gateway.</t>

      <t>When an Oblivious gateway resource sends an HTTP request to an
      Oblivious taget, it adds the "Ohttp-Outside-Encap" header to indicate
      which headers will be removed from the response.</t>

      <t>On receipt of an HTTP response from the Oblivious target resource,
      the Oblivious gateway resource copies the header fields signaled in the
      associated request and removes those headers from the HTTP response. The
      Oblivious gateway then encapsulates the HTTP response. The Oblivious
      gateway resource adds the copied header fields and values to the
      response containing the encapsulated response, so that the Oblivious
      relay can access and act on them.</t>

      <t>The "Ohttp-Outside-Encap" header is useful in deployments where the
      Oblivious gateway resource and Oblivious target resource are managed by
      separate entities.</t>

      <t><xref target="Figure1"></xref> describes the syntax using Augmented
      Backus-Naur Form (ABNF) of the header field, using the grammar defined
      in <xref target="RFC5234"></xref> and the rules defined in Section 5 of
      <xref target="RFC9110"></xref>. The field values of the header field
      conform to the same rules.</t>

      <figure anchor="Figure1" title="Ohttp-Outside-Encap Header Syntax">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
  Ohai-Outside-Encap =  header-field *( OWS "|" OWS header-field)
  header-field = token
]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>Optional white space (OWS) is used as defined in Section 5.6.3 of
      <xref target="RFC9110"></xref>.</t>

      <t>An example is illustrated below:</t>

      <t><figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[Ohttp-Outside-Encap: RateLimit-Limit|RateLimit-Remaining|RateLimit-Reset|RateLimit-Policy]]></artwork>
        </figure></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The security considerations for the Oblivious HTTP protocol (Section
      8 of <xref target="OHTTP"></xref>) as well as the ones for RateLimit
      fields (Section 6 of <xref target="RATELIMIT"></xref>) apply. The
      following sub-sections discuss security considerations specific to this
      specification.</t>

      <section title="Client and Oblivous Proxy Collusion ">
        <t>While Oblivious HTTP relies upon an Oblivious relay to prevent
        leaking the client identity to the Oblivious resources, it might be
        the case that the Oblivious relay colludes with clients in attacking
        Oblivious resources. RateLimit fields might disclose operational
        capacity information useful to design denial of service attacks or to
        circumvent defensive measures put in place by the Oblivious resources
        (Section 6.2 of <xref target="RATELIMIT"></xref>). The Oblivious
        target and gateway resources SHOULD convey Oblivious Relay Feedback
        only to trusted Oblivious proxies.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Attack Categories">
        <t>Attacks against the Oblivious Gateway and Target Resources can be
        classified into three primary categories:</t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t>A client deliberately sends a malformed encapsulated request
            causing decryption failure or decryption overload failure on the
            oblivious gateway resource. This causes the oblivious gateway
            resource to send an error status code back to the oblivious
            relay.</t>

            <t>A client deliberately sends an HTTP request that causes an HTTP
            error on the oblivious target resource. This might be a malformed
            HTTP request, or request for a missing resource.</t>

            <t>A botnet performing an application layer denial of service
            attack (e.g. HTTP flood) against an Oblivious resource. Because
            each bot in a botnet makes seemingly legitimate network requests
            the traffic may appear "normal" in origin, nonetheless as a whole
            it not only can saturate the Oblivious resources, but also makes
            appear the Oblivious relay as an attacker. This might be too many
            requests from a single client, too many requests from the clients
            behind the same oblivious relay or too many requests from all
            clients on the Internet.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <section anchor="enr" title="RateLimit Parameter Value Registrations">
        <t>This specification requests IANA to add the following parameters to
        the "Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) RateLimit Parameters" registry
        defined in <xref target="RATELIMIT"></xref>.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[+=================+=================+================+===============+
| Field Name      |Parameter Name   |Description     |Specification  |
+=================+=================+================+===============+
| RateLimit-Policy|ohttp-target     |ohttp ratelimit |Section 3 of   |
|                 |                 |                |this document  |
| RateLimit-Policy|attack-severity  |ohttp ratelimit |Section 5 of   |
|                 |                 |                |this document  |
+-----------------+-----------------+----------------+---------------+
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Registration of new HTTP Header Field">
        <section anchor="new-header" title="Ohttp-Outside-Encap Header">
          <t>This section describes a header field for registration in the
          Permanent Message Header Field Registry <xref
          target="RFC3864"></xref>.</t>

          <t><list style="hanging">
              <t hangText="Header field name"><vspace
              blankLines="0" />Ohttp-Outside-Encap</t>

              <t hangText="Applicable protocol"><vspace
              blankLines="0" />http</t>

              <t hangText="Status"><vspace blankLines="0" />Standard</t>

              <t hangText="Author/Change controller"><vspace
              blankLines="0" />IETF</t>

              <t hangText="Specification document(s)"><vspace
              blankLines="0" />RFC XXXX</t>

              <t hangText="Related information"><vspace blankLines="0" />This
              header field is only used for Oblivious HTTP.</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Thanks to Lucas Pardue, Rich Salz, Martin Thomson, Christopher A.
      Wood and Brandon Williams for the discussion and comments.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8941'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.9110'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5234'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.3864'?>

      <reference anchor="HTTP">
        <front>
          <title>HTTP Semantics</title>

          <author fullname="Roy T. Fielding">
            <organization>Adobe</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Mark Nottingham">
            <organization>Fastly</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Julian Reschke">
            <organization>greenbytes GmbH</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="12" month="September" year="2021" />

          <abstract>
            <t>The Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) is a stateless
            application- level protocol for distributed, collaborative,
            hypertext information systems. This document describes the overall
            architecture of HTTP, establishes common terminology, and defines
            aspects of the protocol that are shared by all versions. In this
            definition are core protocol elements, extensibility mechanisms,
            and the "http" and "https" Uniform Resource Identifier (URI)
            schemes. This document updates RFC 3864 and obsoletes RFC 2818,
            RFC 7231, RFC 7232, RFC 7233, RFC 7235, RFC 7538, RFC 7615, RFC
            7694, and portions of RFC 7230.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft"
                    value="draft-ietf-httpbis-semantics-19" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="RATELIMIT">
        <front>
          <title>RateLimit Fields for HTTP</title>

          <author fullname="Roberto Polli">
            <organization>Team Digitale, Italian Government</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Alejandro Martinez Ruiz">
            <organization>Red Hat</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="6" month="July" year="2022" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This document defines the RateLimit-Limit, RateLimit-Remaining,
            RateLimit-Reset and RateLimit-Policy fields for HTTP, thus
            allowing servers to publish current service limits and clients to
            shape their request policy and avoid being throttled out.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft"
                    value="draft-ietf-httpapi-ratelimit-headers-05" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="STRUCTURED-FIELDS">
        <front>
          <title>Structured Field Values for HTTP</title>

          <author fullname="M. Nottingham" initials="M." surname="Nottingham">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="P-H. Kamp" initials="P-H." surname="Kamp">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date month="February" year="2021" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This document describes a set of data types and associated
            algorithms that are intended to make it easier and safer to define
            and handle HTTP header and trailer fields, known as "Structured
            Fields", "Structured Headers", or "Structured Trailers". It is
            intended for use by specifications of new HTTP fields that wish to
            use a common syntax that is more restrictive than traditional HTTP
            field values.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8941" />

        <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC8941" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="OHTTP">
        <front>
          <title>Oblivious HTTP</title>

          <author fullname="Martin Thomson">
            <organization>Mozilla</organization>
          </author>

          <author fullname="Christopher A. Wood">
            <organization>Cloudflare</organization>
          </author>

          <date day="15" month="February" year="2022" />

          <abstract>
            <t>This document describes a system for the forwarding of
            encrypted HTTP messages. This allows a client to make multiple
            requests of a server without the server being able to link those
            requests to the client or to identify the requests as having come
            from the same client.</t>
          </abstract>
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-ohai-ohttp-01" />
      </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <reference anchor="SEVERITY"
                 target="https://www.iana.org/assignments/iodef2/iodef2.xhtml#businessimpact-severity">
        <front>
          <title>Incident Object Description Exchange Format v2
          (IODEF)</title>

          <author>
            <organization>IANA</organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Reputation"
                 target="https://identitydocs.akamai.com/getting-started/rba/2-rba/page3-clientrep/">
        <front>
          <title>Client reputation</title>

          <author>
            <organization>IANA</organization>
          </author>

          <date />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <!--
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-httpbis-bcp56bis'?>
-->

      <!--
      <reference anchor="WAF1"
                 target="https://aws.amazon.com/about-aws/whats-new/2020/03/aws-waf-adds-anonymous-ip-list-for-aws-managed-rules/">
        <front>
          <title>AWS WAF adds Anonymous IP List for AWS Managed Rules</title>

          <author fullname="">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="6" month="March" year="2020" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="WAF2"
                 target="https://www.akamai.com/content/dam/site/en/documents/product-brief/web-application-protector-product-brief.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Web Application Protector</title>

          <author fullname="">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="6" month="March" year="2020" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="Slowloris"
                 target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slowloris_(computer_security)">
        <front>
          <title>Slowloris (computer security)</title>

          <author fullname="">
            <organization></organization>
          </author>

          <date day="" month="" year="" />
        </front>
      </reference>
-->

      <!---->
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
